<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Linux on systems++</title><link>http://robertu94.github.io/tags/linux.html</link><description>Recent content in Linux on systems++</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 08:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://robertu94.github.io/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Learning to Learn: Software Development on Linux</title><link>http://robertu94.github.io/learning/development.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://robertu94.github.io/learning/development.html</guid><description>What is software development? At a most basic level, it is the activity of using a programming language to achieve some set of goals over time. It includes everything from scripts that a graduate student might write to analyze some data to massive systems that control aircraft. As our world continues to progress technically, software development will likely become even more commonplace than it is now. In this post, I aim to provide a comprehensive overview of how one can develop software efficiently using free and open source tools on Linux.</description></item><item><title>Learning to Learn: Linux</title><link>http://robertu94.github.io/learning/linux.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://robertu94.github.io/learning/linux.html</guid><description>So you want to or have to try this thing called &amp;ldquo;Linux.&amp;rdquo; Just like curry powder isn&amp;rsquo;t just one thing, but a distinct mix of spices that come together into a tasty mixture, Linux is much the same. Also like curry, Linux isn&amp;rsquo;t for everyone. In this post I describe the process of choosing the &amp;ldquo;flavor&amp;rdquo; of Linux that will work best for you, introduce a powerful tool that will help you to make the most of Linux, and describe some first steps to take when things go wrong.</description></item></channel></rss>