<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Writing on Systems++</title><link>https://robertu94.github.io/tags/writing/</link><description>Recent content in Writing on Systems++</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 06:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://robertu94.github.io/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Learning to Learn: Writing</title><link>https://robertu94.github.io/learning/writing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 06:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://robertu94.github.io/learning/writing/</guid><description>&lt;p>Communication is essential to the enterprise of knowledge.
Without communication, we would never be able to build upon the works of others or have them build upon our own.
One of the most important &amp;ndash; and challenging &amp;ndash; arts within communication is writing.
Writing is unique among commutative forms in its durability and portability.
Once written, the words of the author can transcend even their death and travel places they never dreamed to tread.
However writings portability and durability are the same feature that present its central challenge: With the author long gone, how can the he still communicate his or her intent?
In this post, I ponder how I face these challenges and encourage others to do the same.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Learning to Learn: Studying New Topics</title><link>https://robertu94.github.io/learning/litrature-review/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2019 11:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://robertu94.github.io/learning/litrature-review/</guid><description>&lt;p>Efficient study of a topic is a powerful skill for a wide variety of domains.
However &amp;ndash; despite having several classes on writing and research in High School and Undergraduate Studies &amp;ndash; it wasn&amp;rsquo;t something that I truly appreciated and learned how to do well until Graduate School.
I think this really boils down to lacking the kind of personal application that makes these efforts meaningful.
However now that I have come to appreciate it, I want to highlight how I think how I study new topics, and how this applies to many topics outside of academic research.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>